<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A general epistle to all Friends everywhere, scattered up and down in the world that they all may faithfully keep and walk in the truth of God, as they have received it, thereby to eschew evil and do good in their day and generations / written by a servant of God ... James Park.</title>
            <author>Parke, James, 1636-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56008</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P368</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31067</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11770782</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11770782</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48850</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56008)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48850)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1490:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A general epistle to all Friends everywhere, scattered up and down in the world that they all may faithfully keep and walk in the truth of God, as they have received it, thereby to eschew evil and do good in their day and generations / written by a servant of God ... James Park.</title>
                  <author>Parke, James, 1636-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by T.S. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48850:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48850:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A General Epiſtle To all FRIENDS Every where, Scattered up and down in the WORLD, That they all may faithfully keep and walk in the Truth of God, as they have received it, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to eſchew Evil, and do Good, in their Day and Generation.</p>
            <p>Written by a Servant of God, and Labourer for the Honour of his Name, Proſperity of his Truth, and the Churches Peace and Welfare;</p>
            <p>JAMES PARK.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 13.20, 21.</hi>
               </bibl> Now the God of Peace that brought again from the Dead our Lord Jeſus, that great Shepherd of the Sheep, through the Blood of the Everlaſting Covenant, make you perfect in every good Work, to do his Will, working in you, that which is well-pleaſing in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be Glory for ever and ever; <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Printed, and Sold by <hi>T. S.</hi> at the <hi>Crooked-Billet,</hi> in <hi>Holywell-Lane,</hi> in <hi>Shoreditch,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:48850:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48850:2"/>
            <head>A General Epiſtle to all Friends every where, ſcattered up and down in the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Dear Friends and Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHom I very dearly love in the Covenant of Light and Eternal Life from God made manifeſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have Peace with God, and feel the Joy of his Salvation, which hath been all along, and is our Walls and Bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works of defence, wherein we know Safety and true Reſt and Peace with God through Faith in Chriſt Jeſus; herein do I dearly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member and Salute you all, who are the Sons and Daughters of God, begotten to him by the Word of his Grace and Eternal Life, which liveth and abideth for evermore. Oh! keep all within the Walls and Bullworks of God's Salvation, that will be a ſure De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and as a munition of Rocks to you, where your Bread will be ſure, and your Waters never fail, but the Waters of a full Cup of Bleſſing will be known, and the refreſhing Streams be witneſſed to your heavenly Joy, Comfort and Refreſhment in the Lord, the everlaſting Fountain, from whom all our Comfort, Joy and Refreſhment cometh, in all Storms, Rains, and greateſt Raging of the Sea of wicked and ungodly Men, your everlaſting Rock, Refuge, and hiding Place you know, which is moſt ſure and certain in all the Perils and Dangers that you may meet with in your ſojourning here: flee to your Invincible Rock, Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and you will not fear the Rage of the Wicked, nor be affraid what man can do unto you, whoſe Breath is in his Noſtrils; but then you will only dread and fear the eternal God, and reverence his Name, who keepeth the Feet of his Saints, that none of their Steps may ſlide, but that all may walk uprightly, without ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering at the Promiſes of God, or ſtumbling at any Stumbling-block appearing in your Way and Travel, as Pilgrims in this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48850:3"/>World; then you will not be diſmayed, although the Earth be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved and carried into the midſt of the Sea, now when it is a time of the Lord's ſhaking the Earth, with the Heavens alſo, and all Nations, which are in the Hand of the Lord: and he will ſhake them, and remove the Earth out of its place; and all Nations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, are but as the drop of a Bucket, and the ſmall Duſt of the Ballance; he taketh the Iſlands in his Hand as a very light thing, and doth whatever he pleaſeth in Heaven and in Earth, and in all the Kingdoms of men: and who hath a ſpiritual Eye opened and ſeeth through the vail of Darkneſs, may ſee the Lord won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully ſhaking the old Heaven and the old Earth, and that the old things ſhall paſs away, and all things become new, a new Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and a new Earth, wherein dwells Righteouſneſs: Bleſſed are you that know the old Heavens, the old Earth, with all the old things paſt away, that are quite from them, and ſtand clear from the old Heavens and the old Earth, wherein Unrighteouſneſs is found; for the Lord ſaid, <hi>Behold I make all things new, and rejoyce evermore in that which I creat, for I creat</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>a Rejoycing, and her People a Praiſe.</hi> And this is the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that cometh down from God out of Heaven, as a prepared Bride for her Husband; Mark, as a Bride prepared for her Husband, who is her Maker, the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the midſt of her who is not an unprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but a prepared Bride, for Chriſt Jeſus her Husband.</p>
            <p>And <hi>dear Friends, Brethren</hi> and <hi>Siſters,</hi> bleſſed are you who are come to know the Spirit of God, and a being Married to Chriſt Jeſus, who are come to the general Aſſembly, and Church of the firſt-born, and keep as wiſe Virgins, vigilent, ſober and watchful, being ſtored with the heavenly Oyl in your Veſſels, with your Lamps always kept burning, being ready, and prepared for the Lord's appearing in Power and great Glory; and ſtand upon your Watch-Tower, to oppoſe every appearance of the Enemy, with the Sword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God, very nigh you, with that war againſt the Enemy, that he may not enter again into any of your Hearts to work that which is Evil, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Good wrought or created in any perticular of you, by the Lord God; when the Enemy cometh as a Flood, to tempt, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault, buffet, or winnow you as Wheat, it is to hurt the tender Vines, that they may not grow nor put forth in freſhneſs and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48850:3"/>greenneſs, according to the good end of the heavenly great Planter: and the Enemy would deſtroy the heavenly Babe begotten of God; but you being all armed with the whole Armour of God, waring with the Enemy, the Enemy will flie from you, and will not be able to prevail for to enter any of your Hearts again, by any of his Temptations, Aſſaults, Buffettings or Winnowing, whereby he cometh ſeeking whom of us he may devour: And the Children of the wicked One, know not God, nor that which is begotten or wrought by him, and therefore they ſet themſelves in great Rage and Fury againſt the Lord, and that which he worketh in his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who are begotten to him, and purely live to him, God who hath made you Witneſſes of a Spiritual Warfare, for God and his Works, and againſt the Devil and his Works; and you know the Lord by his Spirit led us on with heavenly Zeal and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, to ſtrike at the Devil and his Works, that are dark and corruptible, that they might be put of; for the Birth and Fruits that are of the Fleſh, cannot pleaſe God; that birth and fruits of the Fleſh muſt be known to dye and wither; for they that are in that Birth, cannot be ſubject to the Righteous Law and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the Lord God. So all muſt come out of that Birth which is of the Fleſh, and the corrupt Nature that came upon Man by his fall from God, whereby he became an evil and corrupt Tree, and brought forth Bryars and Thorns, nigh unto curſing, whoſe end is to be burned, becoming a degenerate Plant, even a Child of a ſtrange Vine unto the Lord, who did plant mankind a noble Vine, a holy and right Seed. My <hi>dear Friends,</hi> feel that right Seed, that God hath ſown in all your Hearts, that in and by the ſame you may all ſtand and remain as noble Plants, in the Vineyard of the Lord, that none of you may be found corrupt Trees that wither, and bring not forth good Fruit, or as them who are twice dead, and plucked up by the Roots, and as wandring Stars, who have left their Habitation that once they had in the Truth; although ſuch may retain the Profeſſion of the Truth, and come amongſt us; but <hi>Friends,</hi> you having an inward Eye opened by the Spirit of the living God, you will ſee them, and beware of them, and avoid their Deceit and Falſehood, in their moſt plauſable Words and fair Speeches, which may tickle the Ears of ſuch as have itching Ears, and draw out the Minds of the Simple to their hurt: But all of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48850:4"/>you mind the Lord God, and eye him in all his Leadings; and whither ſo ever the Lamb goeth, follow him faithfully, even through the greateſt Hardſhips, Difficulties and Tribulation that you may be called to paſs through in this preſent world, of Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and Troubles: Oh! keep going on to Perfection, in the Path of the Juſt, and run the Race that God hath ſet before you with patience, although you meet with many great Troubles and fiery Tryals, look not out, for that is the way that God leadeth his People into his Kingdom of Love, Joy, Reſt and Peace, which is everlaſting; and the great Tribulations which the Righteous meet with for a ſeaſon in this world, and are called to paſs through, is but the more to waſh them and prepare them for that everlaſting Crown and Kingdom, which the faithful God, in what he hath promiſed to the Flock of Chriſt, will certainly give unto them; and whatſoever evil men may do againſt the Church of God, in the execution of their Malice, Violence, Spoils or Ruins, which the Lord hath in many Ages ſuffered to come upon the precious Sons &amp; Daughters of <hi>Sion;</hi> yet in all that which ſuch ſuffered, our heavenly Father deſigned nothing towards them but good, and for their profit, to make them more and more pertakers of his Glory, who in common Calamities and Judgments met with hard meaſure and ſufferings from wicked men, that did not fear God, but were bent to work Wickedneſs, to do it with greedineſs; ſuch now will the Lord judge and recompence the Evil of their own Ways and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings upon their own Heads; and the divine Vengeance of God did overtake, and will overtake ſuch, and with all the Wicked and Unrighteous of the Earth, is the Righteous God pleading, and they ſhall be broken to pieces by him, even like a Potters Veſſel; for they cannot ſtand in Judgment, in the great Day of the Lord, wherein terribly he will ſhake the Earth, that it may be removed out of its place in Peoples hearts; alſo he will ſhake the Heavens, for that is to be ſhaken, that Heaven and Earth may be full of his Glory, and that the Knowledge of the Lord may cover the Earth as the Waters cover the Sea, that Knowledge may be increaſed.</p>
            <p>Now in the woful Day of Judgment &amp; Calamity from God come and coming upon the Wicked and Ungodly; it doth appear to me, as if ſome weak and feeble Ones amongſt us, ſhould ſay, <hi>What will become of us? ſhall me be hid in the Day of the Lord's Wrath? will the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48850:4"/>Lord have pitty upon, and ſpare us, when the overflowing Scourge ſhall paſs through the Land?</hi> This I have to ſay as from God concerning the Righteous every where; Fear not Man, neither be diſmayed at his Looks, becauſe of God's Judgments being in the Earth, or when Calamity cometh; for although Judgments and outward Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity may reach all in general, yet will the Lord remember to ſpare, keep and ſupport the weak of his Flock, that continue with him in Tribulations, and follow him fully, he will give them a Kingdom of Reſt, Joy and Peace, which is everlaſting, the Light of his Countenance ſhall ſhine upon them; he will give them Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for Aſhes, and the heavenly Oyl of Joy inſtead of the Spirit of Heavineſs; that is but for a Night, but Joy cometh in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; the Lord will hide, ſpare and pitty you weak and feeble Ones, in times of Peril, Trouble and greateſt Danger; you abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding faithful unto him, he will not leave you comfortleſs, but will comfort you, and will be a Rock and Refuge to you; for you will find a ſure place of Refuge in his holy Name, in which you have believed, and do truſt; he will not forget you, nor forſake you in your greateſt ſtraits: be patient in Tribulation, for Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion worketh Patience, and patience Experience, and Experience that Hope which maketh not aſhamed, and that will be as an Anchor to hold you all unto, and keep you ſteadfaſt upon the ſure and certain Rock of Ages, Chriſt Jeſus, even from the leaſt of you to the greateſt; and from the weakeſt of you to the ſtrongeſt; and you will mightily be upheld and ſupported by him, in all, through all, and over all, that which God may permit wicked Men, or Devils, to do againſt you, to trouble, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs or try you, who being ſound Righteous, you ſhall have the bleſſed Reward thereof freely beſtowed upon you in this World, and that which is to come, and it ſhall go well with you; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be as to Troubles, Oppreſſions or Tryals in this world, when God's Judgments are in the Earth, and the Vials of his Wrath poured forth with fury upon the Heads of the Wicked and Ungodly, to cut them off; the Lord will have mercy upon <hi>Sion,</hi> he will hear the Cry of the Afflicted true <hi>Sion,</hi> his Bowels of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion will the more appear and be inlarged, to relieve, ſave, help and deliver you, and to cauſe your Enemies to be at Peace with you: God's love and care in watching over his, and to incamp
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48850:5"/>about them, that is a ſure Defence; and a Buckler and Shield will the Lord ever be to all that fear him, and think upon his Name, whether weaker or ſtronger, God who is juſt and equal in all his judgments and wayes; will not deſtroy the Righteous with the wicked, from that great Deluge that came upon the old World, for there great wickedneſs, wherewith they then provoaked the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to great Indignation againſt them; yet he ſaved <hi>Noah</hi> that Preacher of Righteouſneſs and his Family, being Righteous in an <hi>Ark</hi> which <hi>Noah</hi> built, being warned of God to do it long before it was finiſhed; when the Flood came, in that <hi>Ark</hi> was he and his Family ſaved, and not deſtroyed with the wicked: and when God overthrew the Cities of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrow</hi> by a dreadful violent Fire, the deſtroying Angel could not proceed to his work till juſt <hi>Lott</hi> was gone out of <hi>Sodom;</hi> but afterward thoſe Cities were laid in Aſhes. And how did the Lord keep and preſerve that fruitful Bow <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who was hated of his Brethren and ſold by them a Slave into <hi>Aegypt?</hi> how did the Lord help him, ſtand by him and ſtrengthen him, when they agreed to caſt him into the Pit to deſtroy him? did not the Lord cauſe it to work effectually for his good, who by his wiſdom and virtue obtained great favour and honour with King <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Court, and throughout the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> where he was a ſuccour and as a ſaviour to his Father <hi>Jacob's</hi> Family, his envious Brethren that took Counſel together to deſtroy him; <hi>Joſeph</hi> did good unto, and rewarded them good for their envy and cruelty; and the Lord delivered <hi>Jacob</hi> out of all his troubles which he had met with in the dayes of his Pilgrimage, which were many, very great and grevious, as the Scriptures declare; and he that helped, ſaved and delivered the Righteous in all Ages, he is the ſame God now, and changeth not with the times and ſeaſons that are in his Hands, but he will work Wonders for the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our and exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Name, for the Salvation of his choſen Flock, and for the deſtruction of his Enemies that will not bow to him, nor his Government in them, nor over them to reign; and he will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bow them and break them in pieces and ſcatter them in there evil Imaginations, and will bring to nought all the unrighteous deſigns and wicked Conſpiracies of all the wicked and unrighteous in the Earth, to exalt his Name and ſpread his Truth abundantly.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:48850:5"/>
               <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> a great and terrible day of Gods fierce Wrath from Heaven is revealed againſt them that hold the Truth in Unrighteouſneſs, they hold the bare Profeſſion of it, out of the Life and Power thereof, and ſomething of the Form, out of the Power, ſuch do diſhonour God, and are a Scandal to the Name of Chriſt Jeſus, and waver from him, and baulk his Teſtimony, being not faithful to him, nor true in their Teſtimony for thoſe things which we have moſt ſurely believed, to be of and from the Lord. Now his Day is come and coming, that will be upon all found in that ſtate, although they may hold the Profeſſion of the Truth of God, yet they are out of the Poſſeſſion, and they are out of the Kingdom which ſtands in Righteouſneſs, Peace and Joy in the holy Spirit, and are led and guided by an unholy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, into diſobedience to the Lord, and are held Captives there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and ſuch ſhew forth the Rule and Government of the Prince of the power of the Air, having dominion in and over them: Now the terrible Day of God's Wrath will fall heavy on them that obey Unrighteouſneſs, and hold the Truth in Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; and when the Righteous ſhall ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall they appear that hold the Profeſſion of the Truth in Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs? will not ſuch be found amongſt the Hypocrites and Unbelievers? and will not there be Lamentation, Weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and great Wo? and ſhall not Tribulation, Anguiſh and Wrath come upon every Soul of man that doth Evil, of what Name and Profeſſion ſoever they have been of in this preſent world? Now as Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs leads ſuch who are in it, to be faithful in their Teſtimony for God; ſo Unrighteouſneſs doth the contrary, even cauſe many to how their Knee to <hi>Baal</hi> in ſomething or other, to worſhip the Beaſt, and receive his Mark in ſomething or other, more or leſs, which it may be ſuch know that they ought not to fall under in, or to give way unto; and that will bring down Judgment and Wrath from God upon all the diſobedient, who are not juſt, true and faithful in bearing their Teſtimony againſt Wars and Fightings with Carnal Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and againſt Tythes and Offerings, which God in the Goſpel-Day puts an end unto, and requireth not; and that which the Teſtimony of Truth in all the Faithful in our Day,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48850:6"/>hath clearly gone forth againſt from the beginning; and God apparently hath been with his People, and bleſſed us herein: How any can ſlight, go from, or violate that, and directly, or indirectly, joyn with them, or give ſtrength to them that falſify their Teſtimony, making void as much as in them lieth the great and hard Sufferings of many Ancient Friends formerly, who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not their Lives to the Death, ſo that they might fight the good Fight of Faith, and keep their Teſtimony firm and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant for God to the end? And feel the Spirit of Life from God, to enter into you, and poſſeſs all your Hearts, that you may ſtand upon your Feet, and be armed with the Armor of Light, and the Shield of Faith, and the Sword of the Spirit, which proceeds out of the Lamb's Mouth, that faithful Witneſſes for him you may ſtand againſt all that which is Evil, and contrary to the Truth and Teſtimony thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dear Brethren</hi> and <hi>Siſters,</hi> and all <hi>Friends,</hi> who are called of God to do Service in your Men and Womens Meetings, that are of ſuch great tendency for the Welfare and Peace of the Church of God; be diligent to keep up and preſerve your Monthly and Quarterly Meetings, in the pure and peaceable Wiſdom of God, all minding and following thoſe things which are pure, lovely, and of good Report, which makes for Peace; within your Walls of Salvation and Strength from God dwell, and ſtand up for God's Authority, and that all your Men &amp; Womens Meetings therein may be kept, all being diligent and faithful to God, he will be your Shield and exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great Reward; your Shield to defend you againſt all the Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you may meet with, &amp; againſt the Malice &amp; Rage of them that ſeek your hart and overthrow. And be wiſe in Heart in your Words and Actions, do all that you do to the Glory and Praiſe of God, in ſelf-denyal and ſelf-abaſement, conſidering that you act for God, and his Eye is over all; You know that you are not your own, but the Lords, bought with a Price. So all ought faithfully to ſerve, glorifie and honour him, to the uttermoſt of the ſtrength and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity that you have received from God, or may receive in your Day and Generation: Be careful in the fear of the Lord, and then all things will be done decently, and in good order in the Church of God; and let nothing be done in Strife or vain Glory, but do all things in Love, in that dwell together, and edifie one another, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48850:6"/>all things without Partiality, without Hypocriſie, and without Diſſimulation; and keep your Eye ſingle to God, in all whatever you do in Word or Deed, that all may be done in the peaceable Wiſdom of Truth and Righteouſneſs, keeping an equal hand of Judgment and Juſtice without reſpect to Perſons, in all matters and things that may come before you; for ſuch as reſpect the Rich Perſons caſe, more then the caſe of the Poor, may err in Judgment, and commit Sin, and the juſt, equal and righteous Law of God will take hold on ſuch, and judge them, that are found re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting and bearing with the Cauſe of the Rich, becauſe Rich, more then the Cauſe of the Poor of the Flock of God, becauſe they are poor in this World. Wait for Counſel from the Lord, to direct you how to give Advice and Direction unto others, that are but weak in the Faith, and do not ſo clearly ſee their way and work; be tender towards them, and helpful to them in the Lord, and Eyes to them, and Feet to the Lame that have halted, and help them on by a Hand of Love and true Tenderneſs, held forth to them that need it; then will the Lord be with you, bleſs your Meetings, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie and honour them more and more with his holy comfortable Preſence, and give you Dominion and Power over all that which would hurt and deſtroy, or make Schiſms, rend and divide Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber from Member, or the Body from the Head: The Lord hath been with you, and preſerved you together of one Heart, in his buſineſs; and when you have been about your own, his Bleſſing you have felt; and he will be with you, as ye all ſtand, faſt in the Faith, doing his Work unto the end.</p>
            <p>And all you who are Convinced of God's Truth, but not brought to live and walk in it, following your own Wills, Spirits, Paſſions, and vile Affections, not knowing how to bridle your Tongues, nor to keep out of the Evil Words and Ways of the Wicked, but are often catched in the Snares of the Wicked, and led captive by Satan at his Will, tremble before the Lord, fear his holy Name, whilſt God ſpareth you, and ſuffereth you to cumber the Ground; for you fruitleſs Trees cumber the Ground, and muſt be cut down, God will not always ſpare, nor bear with you for your abuſe of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Long-ſuffering; the Lord will judge you, he will plead with you in his Wrath, who follow your own Wills, and ſuffereth your own Spirits, Paſſions and vile Affections to ſway, govern and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48850:7"/>make you Bond-ſlaves, and to keep you faſt Captives to Sin and Satan, which is great ſlavery; and ſo are apt to be drawn into lew'd Company, and to have fellowſhip with them, who are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up to work Wickedneſs, and to hatch Miſchief, and put it in practice; Take heed how you go on in the ways of evil men, take no pleaſure in their company; if ſometimes thou fall into their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany occaſionally or accidentally, without thy ſeeking or deſiring, but with all and care diligence avoid their company; avoid their evil Words, and avoid all their ungodly Converſation, and avoid as much as in you lies Taverns and Ale-houſes, where ſo many wrong their own Souls and Bodies alſo, and impoveriſh their Families, and waſte the Creatures that in themſelves are good, which many may want greatly; and although it be lawful to go to ſuch publick Houſes upon juſt occaſion, or as neceſſity may require it; yet for any to go for Luſt or Faſhion-ſake, and to ſit long with them, who Injuriouſly frequent ſuch Houſes, that hath been a Snare to many Young Men and Women to their great hurt every way; and is no good expedient for the Aged, to ſpend their pretious time unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably in Taverns and Ale-houſes, or any other Houſes where you may receive harm, and bring Reproach upon the Name of the Lord, amongſt wicked and ungodly men and women, who regard not what Wickedneſs they do act, nor what Evil they can tempt and draw others into, deſiring that you that know the Truth might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Companions of Drunkards, Swearers, Lyars, and be made pertakers with them in their ungodly Deeds, whereby ſuch debauch the Minds of all that will have fellowſhip with them, and then rejoyce in their Iniquity, and ſport themſelves, when they have drawn the minds of others out to joyn with them in their abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Practices: Therefore let ſuch as are Convinced of the Truth, and frequent our Meetings, whom this may concern, leave off ſuch Company, and put away all your Iniquities that you are guilty of, and amend your ways and doing, leſt the Lord be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked ſo to Wrath by you, as ſuddainly to cut you off in your Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and it prove your utter Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>And <hi>dear Friends,</hi> be mindful of, and patiently wait for your final Change or the Diſſolution of the earthly Houſe of this Tabernacle; and before, give all diligence to obtain a certain aſſurance, that you have a Houſe not made with Hands, eternal in the Heavens. There
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48850:7"/>are but few mind or conſider how near their Change may be, or when the laſt moment of Time they may have to ſpend in this preſent World ſhall be, many Wiſe men and Prophets of God in our day, are removed and taken away from us, and from the Evil to come, and many other Ancient Friends that ſtood firm in their Day, in Teſtimony to the Lord and his Truth, who had overcome, and were made as Pillars in his Houſe, are fallen aſleep, and are at Reſt from their Labours and Services for the Lord, and Works of Righteouſneſs which they wrought in their Day; let it be your care to remember and follow that good Example they gave you, and left to us all, that we might be one with them, who were faithful Followers of Chriſt Jeſus, and laboured in his univerſal Spirit, and indured much Hardſhip and great Sufferings, but did not ſtagger nor faint in their minds, being of great Courage and Heavenly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution in God's Work, and prepared for their Diſſolution before it came, and their Work was done which the Lord gave them to do: O! be of the ſame Mind and Reſignation to ſerve, pleaſe and follow God, and to finiſh that Work he hath given you to do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be ſaid to you, That <hi>time with you in this World ſhall be no longer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord is ſealing his Servants by his holy Spirit, and hath ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many to the Day of Redemption, ſuch have the mark of God on their Fore-heads, but cannot touch nor receive the mark of the Beaſt on their Fore-heads or in their Hands; the deſtroying Angel muſt not hurt nor harm ſuch, that are ſealed with the holy Seal of the Spirit of God, which all ought to wait for, after you have believed, and feel a fervent Zeal for God as much as ever, being always zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly affected in that which is good, with a circumſpect watch againſt that which is Evil, and every appearance thereof; and keep harmleſs and without fault in the ſight of God, then whoever blame you, or ſpeak evil of you falſly, yet will you be juſtified by the Lord, and clear when he judgeth, that judgeth Righteouſly.</p>
            <p>And beware of all manner of <hi>Deceit, Guile</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> with all <hi>Double-dealing, Diſſimulation, Whiſpering, Tale-bearing,</hi> too much practiſed amongſt ſome profeſſing the pure and precious Truth of God (that come amongſt us) and would be owned as of us, and of the pure Religion, but have not a Bridle for their Tongues, neither take heed to their Sayings or Doings; no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are they ſimple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, but ſubtil, ſome of them, and wiſe to do Evil, ſhuning and avoiding the Plain Language of Truth, according to the Scripture
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48850:8"/>of Truth, which is <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Thou</hi> to a perticular Perſon: But is all ſtood firmly in the Croſs of Chriſt, which is the Power of God, then it would not be ſo with ſuch amongſt us, but they would bring forth Fruits meet for Repentance, and be kept both in the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage and Life of the naked Truth, as it is in Jeſus; For all <hi>Deceit, Diſſimulation, Hypocriſie</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous Coverings</hi> are abhorred of the Lord; and to be <hi>double-tongu'd, double-dealing,</hi> are loathſome and abominable to God, and Good men and women, and as the Scriptures witneſs. O! let all be awakened out of Sleep, and know that now the Day of the Lord is at hand! The Lord is come, who will judge the Secrets of all mens Hearts, as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>According to my Goſpel;</hi> and bring all hidden things to light, as he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, as he ariſeth in Peoples hearts; who will not judge after the ſight of the Eye, or after the hearing of the Ear, or according to appearance; but with Righteous Judgment will he judge both Poor and Rich, High and Low; he will be juſtified when he judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and clear when he condemneth for Sin and Evil: he will do no unrighteouſneſs in Judgment, nor judge as man judgeth, with ſevere and raſh Judgment: He will remember Mercy in the midſt of Judgment; although men are apt to forget it, and not to mix Mercy with their Judgment, but often ſhew Rigour inſtead of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which is not pleaſing to the Lord; for he deſires Mercy ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Sacrifice, and that we hearken to him, that is better than the Fat of Rams.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Friends,</hi> beware of Covetouſneſs, which is Idolatry, and the love of Money, which is the Root of all Evil: how many men heap Sorrows upon Sorrows upon themſelves, by their Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and being overcome with the Cares of this Life, and ſeem as drown'd in Perdition through the love of Money, the Root of all Evil? For what Evil may not ariſe and ſpring from this evil Root? How many evil, hurtful and corrupt Branches that now appear, coming from this pernitious Root in men and women, are daily brought forth to the diſhonour of God, and great Reproach of his Name, by the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in Name only, but not in Nature: and it matters not much what Profeſſion Idolatrous men and women make that ſtill bring forth evil Branches, and evil Fruit from this evil root.</p>
            <p>And beware of Lying, loving or making a Lye, to ſlander, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame or judge another mans Servant, who muſt ſtand or fall to his own Maſter; and God is able to raiſe them up that fall; and he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48850:8"/>that ſtands had as much need as ever to take heed, leſt he fall amongſt them that fall into Miſchief, and leſt he tempt the Lord, and grieve his holy Spirit, which is the cauſe of mans Fall and Miſery, and the Spirit's ceaſing to ſtrive with them that utterly fall, by which Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God we are ſealed to the Day of Redemption, as we abide and walk therein.</p>
            <p>And beware of Unjuſt and Unrighteous Meaſures; but keep to the Ballance of the Sanctuary, which will direct us all to give <hi>Right Weight</hi> and <hi>Meaſure</hi> to others, even ſuch as we deſire they ſhould mete to us; for ſuch meaſure as we mete to others, may be meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to us again; and 'tis but juſt and equal for the equal juſt God to ſuffer it ſo to be, that men hear, fear and underſtand the Rod of Severity that God can make uſe of, when his Favour and Mercy is kicked at and rejected, then an Eye for an Eye, and rendring Evil for Evil, and thinking to overcome the Evil with the Evil, for want of Chriſtian skill to overcome the Evil with the Good.</p>
            <p>And beware of <hi>Hatred, Prejudice</hi> and <hi>Enmity;</hi> envy not one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for becauſe of that the Wrath of God cometh upon the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Diſobedience, although they may know much in compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, or external Notions of the things of God, in the head or brain, and be ſwelled and lifted up therewith; for that Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that is out of the Life and Simplicity of the Goſpel, will hurt, and not heal, or pour Oyl into the Wound, to heal the Hurts or Bruiſes of the Daughter of God's People; and what Hurt, Envy, Hatred and Prejudice hath done amongſt men, is ſo obvious, that much need not be ſaid to demonſtrate it, for all may ſee or hear of the <hi>Murders</hi> and <hi>Bloodſheds</hi> that are in the World, the many <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates</hi> and <hi>Duels</hi> amongſt Men, and how they kill one another in their heat of <hi>Paſſion, Malice</hi> and <hi>Envy;</hi> and he that doth envy his Brother is a Murderer in his heart, and hath not eternal Life abiding in him: and the Treachery that is amongſt men, their betraying one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Death, it oftentimes doth ariſe and come from that bitter Root of Prejudice and Envy, which is the work of the Devil. But all <hi>Friends</hi> every where, keep out of thoſe things that gender to Strife, Contention, or doth provoke to Evil, or to any manner of Sin, but exerciſe your ſelves unto Godlineſs, ceaſe from Anger and for ſake Wrath, fret not your ſelves in any wiſe to do Evil; for Evil-doers ſhall be cut off; follow the things that make for Peace,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48850:9"/>and you ſhall enjoy Reſt, Peace and Quiet, and know the perfect love of God, to caſt out the fear of man, or what man can do, when others are full of Fears and Unbelief, becauſe of evil Tidings, and concerning future things that may come to paſs; dwell in the Love of God and perfect Charity one towards another, and the Lord will be a Shelter and Hiding Place to you.</p>
            <p>And take heed of <hi>Whimſies,</hi> or <hi>Imaginary vain Conceits,</hi> and then to think of your ſelves above what is mete; but all keep low in your minds, and be little in your own Eyes; for ſome being blown up into high Conceits, are hurried into uncertain Sounds, and flaſhes of falſe Joy, which is not the Joy of the Lord, that is ſtrength to the Righteous, neither doth tend to the Good or Edification of the Church of Chriſt; howbeit, put on <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Charity, and bear one with another, more eſpecially in publick Aſſemblies: We ought to bear with ſome Weakneſſes, rather then cruſh or hurt any thing that is good and right; have Charity towards the Weak, and bear one anothers Burdens, that Peace, Order and Unity in the Spirit may be kept in all the Churches of Chriſt: And as much as in you lies, live peaceably with all men, and in the Spirit of God pray for all men, high and low, rich and poor: And obey Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ſo far as you may with a ſafe Conſcience, or your Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for the Truth will admit, that under them we may live a ſober righteous Life in all Godlineſs and Honeſty, that whereas many ſpeak againſt us as Evil-doers, they may be aſhamed, &amp; acknowledge to your upright Godly Converſation, coupled with fear, to do an evil thing, to harm or be injurious to any man.</p>
            <p>And beware of <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>vain Glory,</hi> with the <hi>vain</hi> and the <hi>fooliſh Faſhions</hi> of this periſhing world, that paſſeth away, keep out of all <hi>ſpiritual Pride,</hi> let it not have place in any of your Hearts, and hide it not from your Eyes, <hi>for God beholds the Proud afar off;</hi> and would any of you have God to behold you afar off; and ſuch as God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds afar off, are not near him; for who are near him, he doth behold them ſo, they are precious in his ſight, his Eyes are over them, and he giveth them more Grace: but he reſiſteth the Proud; <hi>a high Mind goeth before a Fall, and Pride before Deſtruction;</hi> and it hath brought Wo and Deſtruction upon many; and but few hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves under the mighty Hand of God, lowlineſs of mind, and humility. Therefore all keep in, give not way to any proud
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48850:9"/>Deſires of your Hearts, from whence cometh Proud Words, and inclinations after high Attire, ſhining and coſtly Apparel outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, affecting the Antick Fantaſtical Faſhions of the World, which too many profeſſing God's plain Truth get into, and delight them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And all you</hi> Elder Men <hi>and</hi> Women, <hi>profeſſing the holy pure plain Truth of God, be good Examples in Plainneſs, Purity and Holineſs, unto the Younger Men, Women and Children, in your Lives and Converſations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you come; wear nothing, neither ſpeak or do any thing but that which is Grave and Savoury, becoming Godlineſs, which may reach to the Good, and that which is of God in all may own, approve and juſtifie you in; the Younger look at you who are Elder, and when or wherein any of you take li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to faſhion your ſelves like unto this World: How can you expect but that the Younger Men, and Women, and Children, will in that be apt to follow your Example; and when you ſpeak rude unſavoury Words, may not you be ill Inſtruments to corrupt the good Manners of the younger ſort of People amongſt us? And when you that are Elders, do any thing againſt the pure Truth of God, and the Younger behold you, may not that hurt and defile them? and ſo you become Miniſters of Evil things to the weak and Young, and grieve the Spirit of God in them, and alſo in your ſelves, which ſhould ſeal you to the Day of Redemption, and would keep the Crown of Pride from you all, if you would keep in the Spirit of God, and be led and guided by it; for that never led, nor will ever lead any to ſpeak, do, or wear any thing unbecoming the Truth or Godlineſs. I know that by the Worldly Liberty, which ſome Elder men and women among us have taken in Words, Deeds and Habits, out of the Truth, and condemned by it, they have but weakened themſelves, brought a Vail over the Seed of God in them, and rendered themſelves leſs uſeful to ſerve God and his precious Truth in their Generation; and all evil Words, evil Deeds, or evil Faſhions, ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, done or followed, are a diſ-ſervice to the Truth, works againſt it, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a ſlight eſteem of it, and doth tend to hinder the Proſperity of it. And therefore every one of you profeſſing the Truth, keep out of that which works againſt it, and bringeth diſhonour to it; What manner of Perſons ought we to be in all holy Converſation and Godlineſs, who know the Truth of God, to keep in his fear at all times, to fear to offend him or grieve his holy Spirit, in Words or Actions, or by giving any way to Pride or High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindedneſs in any thing what we ſay or do. And in our Apparel, men and women eſpecially, the Elder ſort, to be plain and modeſt, and all to behave themſelves in Sobriety and Moderation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:48850:10"/>
               <hi>And you</hi> Friends, <hi>that are Rich, and have plenty of created Comforts in this World, let not your Table become your Snare, nor that which was given you, for your Welfare become your Trap, and with-hold any of you from God, or your Duty, wherein you ought to be found conſtant to him; but be wiſe, and ſhew forth</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Moderation in the right uſe of all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and keep out of that Exceſs which the World, and worldly Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors take liberty in, and ſport themſelves in the practice of, in their Eating and Drinking at Marriage Feaſts, and other Feaſts: Oh! what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>luttening Rioting and Wantonneſs are even many found in! which ſorely diſpleaſeth the Lord, kindles his Wrath, and that which they have cauſe to be aſhamed of, and ſuch indeed as is a ſhame to</hi> Chriſtianity, <hi>in the Life of it; for that is that which we are to mind, and keep to the ancient practice and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the</hi> Primitive Chriſtians, <hi>in our Eating and Drinking, Marriages, Apparelling our ſelves, that whether we eat or drink, or whatſoever we do, or take in hand, that all may be done to the Praiſe and Honour of God, in pure mindedneſs to give Thanks unto God the Father, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who dyed for us and all men, and did purchaſe us with his own Blood, that we all might know Remiſſion of Sin, and know the Deeds of the Body mortified, and the Old man with his Deeds, that are corruptible put off; and to be covered with and adorned with the Heavenly Man, who is from above, and he, nor the glory of his Kingdom is of this world: O let all come to bear his Image, be willing to be made by him conformable to him who is from above, and above all, that your Wills or Affections may not go out after, or be ſet upon any thing that is Viſible, or Temporal; but with a pure Eye look to him who is from Everlaſting to Everlaſting, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible and Eternal; let your Minds and Affections go after him, and be ſet upon him; and thoſe things which are Inviſible and Eternal, all wait more and more to love and take pleaſure in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all <hi>dear Friends</hi> and <hi>Brethren</hi> every where, having received the Spirit of God poured forth from him, keep therein, for its good and profitable to be in the Spirit of God; and that tends to Godlineſs, which is profitable in all things, having the promiſe of this Life, and that which is to come: and Pray often in the Spirit of God, having a Spiritual Mind and Underſtanding alſo: Pray to God the Father, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that you may be kept ſtedfaſt to him, and preſerved in Purity to his praiſe, whilſt in this preſent World. O! be ye all fervent in Prayer and Supplications to God, that you may abide faithful to him in your Words and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48850:10"/>and that Teſtimony God hath called you to bear for him and his Truth; be righteous, true and faithful therein, and grow up as Pillars in his Houſe, and not to defile your Garments any more with the Polutions of this evil World, but conſtantly be kept to God out of Sin &amp; Evil, throughout your Pilgrimage in it: be tender oue towards another, and pray one for another in the love of God, that you may be kept always abounding in it; and love and pray for your Enemies, and do good to them that hate you, and pray for them that deſpitefully uſe and perſecute you, conſidering that the Prayers of the Righteous the Lord doth hear, regard and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and their fervent Prayers in the Name of Chriſt prevails much with God, and availeth much for the good of his Church, and alſo for the benefit of the Children of men in general, that have not ſinned out their day, nor are finally given up to utter Ruin and Deſtruction. And my <hi>Friends,</hi> in every thing that you do receive from God, give humble and hearty Thanks to him; and be you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways contented with what you do receive from him, whether it be that which may appear Evil or Good, Affliction or Proſperity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Poor or Rich, in every ſtate be contented, with your lot and portion in this world; and ſhut out all murmuring againſt the Lord, and all evil Thoughts and Grudgings one againſt another; be content with ſuch things as you have, conſidring that we brought nothing with us into this world, neither muſt we carry any thing out with us when we go away out of it; and in it there is no long continuance.</p>
            <p>And you that are but weak in the Faith, or have but a little Faith, neither have ſo much Wiſdom and Knowledge, as may be others have, let not the weakneſs of thy Faith, or want of that Wiſdom and Knowledge that others may have, at all diſcourage thee, or raiſe any Doubts, Reaſonings, or Queſtionings in thy mind, that God will not hear or regard thy Prayers, being in the leaſt meaſure of the Spirit of God offered to him; for he will both hear and anſwer thy Prayers that are in the living Faith, without doubtings and reaſoning of the Fleſh, notwithſtanding thy weakneſs or little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thy Wiſdom and Knowledge; and if thou know not how to pray, nor what to ask, wait for the Spirit, and to feel Life there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ariſe and move in thy heart, for that will help thy Infirmities, with Sighs and Groans that cannot be uttered forth in words, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48850:11"/>he knoweth the mind of his own holy Spirit; for it moves to Holineſs, to that which is good, but not to that which is evil, in any man or woman; but to avoid that which is evil in all Thoughts, Words and Actions: our God knoweth the mind of his own Spirit, in a holy Deſire or pure Meditation, without Words, as well as with Words ſpoken forth.</p>
            <p>Therefore my <hi>dear Friends,</hi> let none of you ſtruggle or ſtrive in your own Wills to uſe many Words or Repetitions in Prayer to God the Father, but feel his Spirit to move in all your Hearts; for that will ſufficiently help your Infirmities, and teach you how to make your Requeſts in Prayer to God, who knoweth what you ſtand in need of.</p>
            <p>So <hi>dear Friends,</hi> I do commit you to God, and his Spirit of Truth in all your Hearts, that that therein you may all ſerve, worſhip, and pray unto him, and that you may pleaſe the Lord in all things, is the fervent breathing Deſires of your Friend and Brother, in a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Relation in and through God, and Chriſt Jeſus, the only Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and Mediator betwixt God and Man, who ever liveth, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Interceſſion for all the Saints.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Hoſleydown,</hi> 
                  <date>the 18th of the 6th <hi>Month,</hi> 1691.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48850:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
